Thanks for coming at reasonable short notice.
I guess
we're looking for a bit of an update, and I know that the various
members of the committee do have some questions.
So,
we're in your hands.
Perfect. Manny, do you want to just give a little bit of an update?
Of course. So we haven't found any further detections.
So that is still the current state.
So three detections in the Wellington
bottom of the south, sorry, South of the North Island region.
All of those in wild birds, one of them in
the
carrier, two in pelagic
seabirds, ones that come from the Southern Ocean and then make
landfall in either or Australia. Still the situation.
Surveillance continues.
Public still continue to report to the exotic pest and disease hotline, which we're
very grateful for.
Surveillance continues at the
various wildlife hospitals and those we'll run through to the
exotic pest and disease hotline as required.
No detections in poultry,
and the readiness activities with the poultry industry
continue to progress. So.
Right.
So we'll go to questions.
Yeah.
Yeah. Thank you, Chair. Thank you.
I just wanted to touch base about the correspondence,
about the rules around hens.
Mm-hmm.
And
obviously, NAWAC is undertaking their review of the Code of Welfare,
and that they are proposing that to be permanent.
Yes, my concern is that,
it appears from the correspondence that the reason they're proposing that is
because there isn't an opportunity to make a temporary change,
in the case of a biosecurity
incident.
I guess my question is,
we're currently, and we've just had the committee stage of the Emergency
Management Bill. This could potentially
be included in that bill, potentially.
So I'd be interested in whether you sought any advice on whether it would be
considered, because a biosecurity outbreak can potentially be
part of emergency management. And so whether any advice was
sought on whether that would've been a better mechanism to use so that you can make
a temporary adjustment. Because no one, I think, disagrees that there will be times
when you need to make a temporary adjustment.
But it seems
it's at odds with our animal welfare obligations to be making a permanent
adjustment.
So what I'm interested in is whether any advice was sought on
other legal mechanisms that could've been used so that a
temporary adjustment could be made.
Lisa, do you want me to touch on that?
Yeah, I can do that.
So I guess that I would open by saying that our Animal
Welfare Act in New Zealand sets minimum
expectations for the way we look after animals.
So,
looking to adjust those lower than the minimum isn't something
that we have generally spent a lot of time on.
So, the kind of concept of allowing
inappropriate treatment of animals in certain circumstances is not something that
is built into the Animal Welfare Act.
That said, we do have mechanisms to manage the
biosecurity elements of incidents.
I think if we separate that question from the question about the hens,
so NAWAC's--
there's kind of two elements to their deliberations around the hens
code elements. One is the fact
that, on reviewing the science, they have
decided, and to consult on
changing the standard for the stocking
density to nine hens per square meter because they
consider that science does not support seven,
and seven is certainly out of step with all other standards
around the world.
So
they are saying, in their view, nine is an appropriate
minimum standard for New Zealand's animal welfare.
And so there is no need then to look at any sort of a temporary change.
The second element is the fact that bird flu has arrived.
We're expecting it'll become an endemic disease
in New Zealand, as with everywhere else.
And the decisions about management of
stock in any case where we have endemic diseases is
for the owner of that stock to make decisions on a case-by-case basis
based on the risk. And the risk is dependent on a variety of things,
including the environmental factors, what's happening around, but also the
mechanisms that
that farmer uses to manage their stock.
So at the moment, we have a variety of approaches taken by different
layer hen producers, based on their
personal appetite for business loss as well as their
normal operations and their management of risk.
So we would expect to see those kinds of decisions being taken
independently by individual operators on an ongoing basis.
And so decisions to bring birds in or out will be taken in that way
rather than controlled by a central government or other central kind of
decision maker.
So I guess, I've got a few follow-up questions.
So while I appreciate this is NAWAC's approach is and not MPI's
itself,
I guess I would assume that they would be seeking some advice or some secretarial
support from MPI.
Mm-hmm.
My question is, the top of the letter that you wrote to us
said that what triggered this, though, was the bird flu.
This is what triggered the discussion point.
And so my question was quite specific.
What other options did you look at in terms of trying to address this?
So was there advice sought on whether a
large-scale outbreak would meet the criteria for emergency
management? So yes, Emergency Management is its own act, but there are a range of
different types of emergencies that can occur that can then trigger emergency
management, and
it doesn't have to be a natural disaster.
COVID, for example, was a health
emergency.
Mm-hmm.
So
my question is-
Yeah
... did you seek that as an option instead so that you
can make a temporary adjustment rather than actually having a
permanent change to the Code of Welfare?
Well, like I say,
the concept of temporary reductions in animal welfare is not
something that MPI is
generally seeking,
and nor our go-to policy response.
We do think that
biosecurity risk can be managed in ways without
compromising animal welfare. So the concept itself is not
our usual go-to.
In this case, the request to NAWAC was triggered from the
minister. He sought a specific and kind of quick
turnaround compared to the more standard, fuller, longer
process to look specifically at elements that might allow
for movement of hens, and the trigger was the bird
flu.
That doesn't change NAWAC's process, which is that they must consider the
science. So they looked at a range of options when they
started to consider the issue,
and my understanding is that they considered a temporary option,
and their view was, like I said, because of the
expectation this disease will become endemic and that decisions
will need to be made on a very localized basis, and that there's an element there
of the individual business decision around risk appetite and so on,
that it wasn't a suitable kind of an activity for there to be a
central controller of that.
So-
And we'll-- Sorry. We'll also obviously review both the consultation
ourselves, and I think the complexity, it's a good question round
about what parts of the act for emergencies, but animal welfare
remains the primary consideration.
Then there's the resilience whilst
preparing for the potential that it will be endemic in
the space. So we have to look at that factor for the poultry industry
in terms of resilience in the future.
And then the third thing is about resilience and food security.
So you've got all the competing factors of that to get the balance
right. NAWAC's,
as Lisa said, looked at the current code and
have provided
the consultation document to look at, but we'll also balance that as well
as we always do in terms of our advice to the minister.
The challenge from my perspective will be around about
if it does get into poultry, then what's the potential benefits
and trade-offs of an emergency solution rather than a full-time solution that
covers all of what I've just said, the animal welfare, making sure we're
prepared for HPAI and make sure we limit the spread where we can,
but also the resilience in food security.
So I've got a couple questions. One is,
so if you've got hens packed in closer together, doesn't that potentially
make the spread,
like actually make the spread happen more, like go faster?
Doesn't that increase the risk of spread or-
No.
In a situation, if animals are densely housed and
biosecurity is poor, then that is indeed the case,
that densely housed animals will spread between themselves.
The industry is working
on improving biosecurity so that the disease can stay out of
sheds, and that is literally one of the only things that they can do,
is to increase biosecurity at the shed and farm level to stop the
disease coming in.
So why does making them more densely contained
help as a response to bird flu?
Well, I can probably answer that. I think it's less about the more
densely contained, and it's more about the fact that at the moment we have two
different standards. One for
birds and layer hens that have access to an outdoor area during the
day,
and a second standard for layer hens that do not have access to an outdoor area.
So at the moment, the standard for layer hens that do not have access to the
outdoor area is seven,
and for those that do have it's nine.
And the nine
was decided to do with the fact that at certain times of the day, the
hens have a bigger space to access.
So like I say, the science is being reviewed, and it's considered that nine is a
sufficient amount of space. I think the link to the HPAI
is the fact that if you have
outdoors-living birds, that they are mixing in and out and they
have the
nine requirement, at the moment under the
code, you wouldn't just be allowed to move all of those birds inside your shed
and keep them inside until you felt it was appropriate to let them out.
That's right.
Because then you would have this nine stocking, but you would have birds living
indoors. So at the moment, the farmers don't have
that flexibility. They would need to cull birds or otherwise dispose of
some birds in some other way, maybe to a friendly neighbor farm who's got
some space or whatever. But they don't have that flexibility right
now. So the purpose of allowing, of
aligning the standards was to allow flexibility and management
to allow quick on-the-ground decisions.
Just one final question.
Last one.
Yeah. Did you
or did NAWAC
seek advice around impact on the UK and
EU free trade agreements, which have got animal welfare clauses in them,
where New Zealand has said we will not reduce any of our animal welfare standards,
and whether these changes could potentially breach-
And I recognize that the UK and EU have got,
that what we're proposing is more likely to match that, but that's not actually the
point. The point is that the agreements look at us reducing
any of our
regulations. So just wondering if any advice was sought on whether it would
potentially breach any of the FTAs.
I think MFAT are best placed to legal opinion on that.
But as far as we're aware that there's no specific obligations
under that NZ-EU ETA that would be impacted by this change.
But did you ask MFAT for advice on that?
Not at this stage, but again, we'll continue in terms of through the
consultation, through the process and our review and our advice back to the
minister.
Do the officials have any-
Just going to say at this point, it's not my responsibility to
consider that. That'll be an obligation for us as
we advise the minister around the code if it's reported back.
So we'll need to have that conversation with our MFAT and our trade
international colleague.
Yeah.
Sue's had a question.
Oh, you sort of answered it, but triggered another one maybe.
So is this basically free-range birds that are then going to be
required to be kept inside? Is that essentially what you're talking about?
Or am I going on the wrong track?
That is essentially what we're talking about, but the decision to keep them inside
is the businesses. So there's no requirement to keep your bird inside, but you may
choose to do so in order to protect it.
So no matter how bad it gets, it will always be up to the individual business
owners to determine what to do. And then, for example, if they do decide to keep
them inside, at what point are the eggs they produce no longer free-range?
It's a great Fair Trading Act question.
And I believe that we have had some conversations with MB on
that. And I think that Egg Industry is in conversations with the Commerce
Commission around what's an appropriate correct labeling. Is that right?
That's correct.
Because last time when we met, I said that
some of the actual egg farmers hadn't had a lot of feedback, that you guys had been
talking to the industry, but it hadn't sort of trickled down.
And that was one of the questions that I did get asked, do they have to change
their packaging? Should they be ordering packaging, or will it be okay to
stick a label on it to say, "Actually, no."
So we did have a webinar with all of the egg producers the other
day.
Fantastic. Thank you.
And there was a discussion about this.
There has been conversations with the Commerce Commission about
this disease and the impacts it's had internationally and what the approaches there
have been. The industry is also, they've showed me the stickers that they
have that they can stick on things.
This is actually quite labor-intensive and difficult.
Yes.
And so there are ongoing conversations between the industry
and supermarkets and the Commerce Commission. So this is definitely ongoing.
We also, at that webinar, presented
some maps showing testing in different
places and had a discussion about how
farmers might be able to interpret that testing and different detections
to understand their risk when they make these
decisions.
Steve.
Thank you. Different line of questioning.
We visited BirdCare Aotearoa recently,
who were at pains to say that their main message was call the 800 number if you see
any birds behaving strangely. They are a
well-known location for people taking sick birds of all type.
They were previously bird rescue, and they're known sort
of in the community beyond simply
things that are communicated publicly, if you know what I mean.
So their concern is they're wanting to set up some sort of
triage at the gate for people who are going to turn up with sick birds, even though
people have been told not to touch the birds.
Mm-hmm.
They're concerned people won't follow those instructions, and they might either try
and look after themselves and take them home and
they're very much across the need to
deal with the
fundamental problem. But they're concerned that they don't have the ability to
separate birds that haven't got the virus from ones
that do, and that the public interacting with
them will cause the problem to be worse.
I wonder, have you engaged with them directly, and are you
able to support their call for some assistance in setting up
a triage in West Auckland? That's the first
question. And the second question is,
there was a discussion about if this were to get into the gannet colony, for
example, out at Muriwai or other places like that, and there would be a large-scale
death toll,
sadly.
Whether there was regarded as zero value in
trying to deal with carcasses in an
appropriate way
to stop the spread because obviously other birds or other
animals will come and
interact with those carcasses.
And it did strike me that in terms of stopping the curve
of infection, not because we're going to eliminate it, but because we're going to
try and break the curve, then is there some place for,
in an instance like that, where you've got a large bird
that lived potentially by a large populous area of humans and
other animals, whether there's a place for large-scale
burials. And I know that on those Black Sound West Coast beaches of Whangamutoto,
we bury whales and things, so we could bury a whole lot
of birds.
Two questions.
Do you want to take them?
Yes.
Or do you want to talk about your engagement with the hospitals? Simon.
So for the rehab centers, we spoke to BirdCare
Aotearoa the other day.
Mm-hmm.
There's about 46
rehab for birds around the country.
Mm-hmm.
So we've been talking to an initial 20, and we're
ringing the others at the moment to work out what their needs are and how they're
getting on at the moment. And
Pretty positive feedback from most of them, actually.
They're managing all right at the moment.
With BirdCare Aotearoa,
they're really keen to set up that isolation unit, and that's
obviously got a cost to it,
and also some additional staff to help them work seven days a
week. So we're working through how we could
support them if we can,
but also bearing in mind that there's another 45 that are
also
probably going to look for some help if we get into this stage.
Yeah.
One option that we might look at is if we can offer some kind of grant
scheme that people can apply for additional help.
But obviously,
early days on how we go about that at the moment.
The other thing with the BirdCare establishment is it's one of the
five
wildlife hospitals that we have a contract with to do
swabbing on a routine basis.
Mm-hmm.
So we increased that contract earlier this year in anticipation of the
additional work.
Yeah.
And we could also look at
is there anything else in that contract arrangement that we could provide
additional support for as well.
Okay. Yeah.
So we are working on this, and we do realize that although
the advice might be leave birds where you find them and-
Yeah
... people are still going to want to help-
... and still going to take birds somewhere.
So we have to
accept that that's going to happen and provide support where we can.
Yeah.
As we move through this
over the next few weeks, months, and it changes because we'll have
a lot more birds, we'll have a lot more virus
around, and
it will change over time. So some of the rehab outfits have got to have a
think about what's their operating model as they get busier moving forward.
Yeah.
So
we'll work that out as we go, I guess.
It's hard to predict how different types of birds will react to the
virus.
On the-
Sorry, the main point I think you've raised is that
they're massively valuable to have a strong strategic partnership for
this.
Yes.
They've already put, obviously, the value of two of the detections came through
these rehab hospitals who are extremely conscious that we've got to work closely,
take on board their feedback, and set up any partnerships that assist, including
the discussion that Angus and the team had this week.
So
we need to maintain that strong partnership with these providers
as we continue to prepare and make sure that we're ready.
Yeah. That's great to hear because I think there's a real resource
there, and they're keen to help, and
they're very well-connected in the local area.
Communities and-
Yeah. All that stuff
... volunteer organizations. Absolutely.
Sorry. Do you want me to answer the disposal?
Yes.
So on the disposal side of things, it's
a huge amount of work going on in that area across the
board.
So with
mass die-offs,
it depends really who the landowner is.
So it might be councils, it might be a private landowner, it might be
DOC. Could be any of those. So
we've got to work with them around
what the most suitable way to either leave things where they are or dispose
of them.
If it's really accessible to the public, we might have a different approach to
one that nobody ever gets to. So
we did a webinar this morning with, I think there was about 140 people
from all the councils looking at composting.
So that's an option that
might be a real
easy way to dispose of large numbers of birds, particularly poultry.
But also,
if we get large die-offs of seals or that kind of thing.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
But we're looking at every option is kind of what I'm saying, whether
that's burial on site where they are,
burial somewhere else or landfill or whatever.
And that could minimize the spread somewhat.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
Mary?
So I think there's limited scientific information about if
moving those things and burying them and having the people in and out to do that
work is a plus or a minus in terms of spread.
Right.
So I think we just need to keep that in mind.
Yeah.
Certainly when we want to decrease the ability for
people and pets and things to interact with them.
Yeah.
So in places where there is lots of traffic and things, obviously
then these things become really important.
But in terms of the scientific data about if
burying everything or moving them actually helps or not-
Yeah
... I think the jury is pretty much out on that.
Right. Okay.
Yeah. Internationally although, yeah.
So
in my electorate, Oamaru has a harbor with lots
of native birds, shags,
penguin seals,
and
if there was to be a large scale event,
I imagine it would be several sites around the country, and
MPI just won't be able to get to every site.
So are you confident that the regional council,
local council, and NGOs in those areas are
able to deal with
something like that? Because I'd assume
the
dead animals will have to be removed from the harbor in Oamaru
because you're going to have tourists and there's a lot of people there then.
So I-
And that's how you spread it too, right?
Yeah, so.
I spoke to Mayor Tuppendale, is it?
Yeah.
Yesterday, I think, so talking about exactly that situation
where if they get a large number of animals around the harbor, how we
can address that. So we're going to have a follow-up meeting.
She's going to bring all the council staff in.
I think where we're going to get to is that
it's best endeavors by all the partners-
Yeah
... and all the stakeholders. And if a particular council or
landowner hasn't got the resources to deal with it, then we're going to have to
have a look around the wider family and provide that
support.
Okay.
Yeah.
And
for those
endangered species that we have, in my case
it's yellow-eyed penguins, little blue penguins.
There's
others around the country that
for wild animals will be reasonably easy to vaccinate because they're
coming ashore into a nest every night.
How
available are those vaccines for those different groups?
So at the moment, the vaccination
program that DOC administers is
under emergency-
Use
... use because of the, and the emergency is that
the populations identified could become extinct at a national level.
Yes.
And Kat can take it from there.
Yeah. So at the moment, that's exactly the case.
So for example, the korora is not on that list,
and
where we're at is-
Yeah
... where we're at is we will vaccinate those that are most
at risk, and then the rest, it's the other measures that we can
take. So really good biosecurity, good pest control,
dog control, other things like that, that will impact on
birds
who will inevitably be impacted by the disease.
But the
vaccination is
a small part of that bigger
picture for us.
Just a very quick, so I understand, but are you saying you will vaccinate hoiho,
for example?
But regionally-
When, yeah
... yeah. Regionally also, little blue penguin
may not be nationally threatened, but in a local area, if you lose the
entire population, that has a very significant effect,
because that population's gone.
Yeah.
And in that region, it's gone. So are you thinking in those terms as well?
Is there a scarcity of vaccine? Because it does seem in the
case of
little blue penguin, it would be great if regionally you could protect certain
populations.
Yeah. So again, it's very much at that
extinction level that we're looking to protect because it's only
one small tool and actually the things that are more effective are
the other
measures that you can take. So,
I think there's a risk that we could say vaccinating is going to fix this
problem. The answer is it's absolutely not.
Mm.
It's very much a backstop for us for those species
that are most at risk. So at a local level, what
we're
telling people, and we've also held a number of webinars, I think we've held six so
far. We've had up to 400 people on some of those
calls from wildlife centers, et cetera, around the country.
But very much the message is it's those other things that you can do that will be
most effective, particularly for those local populations where we know birds are at
risk.
Because it doesn't work on chicks, does
it? They've got to be a certain age, don't they, the animals, before you can
get-
So we can vaccinate
birds with the current vaccines that we have.
They need one injection in one month.
So start here, whatever age they are.
Yep.
Then a month later.
And then after six months, and then, so this is an ongoing
repeatable process. I just need to stress as well, it doesn't stop them from
getting the disease.
No.
Mm-hmm.
And so we don't know then if they are going to be completely protected or not,
right? We also don't know if they will still be able to pass it to another bird,
okay? Even if they don't die themselves.
Yeah.
And so-
And you would expect they would, though
... you're just keeping them alive, but they're still infectious.
That's possible. Similar to humans with influenza, right?
Right.
Exactly the same, and so that is the situation that we have, which is
why this is a limited tool when we're talking about critically
endangered species at the national level where every individual
counts.
Yes.
It's also very invasive. So-
Yeah
... if you're going into a wild bird population, capturing,
that's quite a stressful situation.
And then you have to recapture again the same bird six months
later.
But it's worth risk we've taken for hoiho.
For, yeah, for particularly takahe, kaki,
kakapo. Those birds, for kakapo, for example, they're all tagged.
We know exactly where they are. We know we can go there once.
We know we can go back and get them again.
And when you've only got a couple of hundred birds,
it's vital that we've got some protected.
Yeah.
And how much per shot?
That's the next question.
The cost?
Yeah.
So I think the vaccine has been donated,
so there is no cost for the vaccine.
But the cost comes-
But there's a cost for the administration.
That's correct. Yeah.
So have you factored that in?
Yep.
Do you know how much yet?
We have. So the exact figure is 100 and-
150,000 for tranche one
... 150,000 for tranche one. What we've also been doing is training up a bit of a
workforce of other people who can vaccinate, so people at wildlife centers,
vets, et cetera, so that we're expanding the number of people and taking a bit of
pressure off the small initial team.
So that's the first injection for all of those birds, tranche one?
Yep.
No, tranche one is-
Tranche one is-
... bonus jabs for the five species that are part of tranche one.
This is good value.
So how many-
Considering how hard it is to get species back.
Yeah.
It's because they're all captive.
Oh, gotcha.
Thank you very much.
Any further questions?
We've come to time, but thanks very much.
I guess we could stress that it's really important to continue
with your good work and to continue engaging with
those communities and making sure that councils, et cetera, are actually
talking to their NGOs as well.
And ComCom-
Yeah
... feed back to the
bird, the-
Yeah,
and I think the chicken, the poultry
groups might be getting the information, but I don't know if every single farmer
still is. So
thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thanks very much.
Great. Mile.
Thank you.
See you again